today I'm talking to Jonathan pazzo who
I think is touched with more than a
little bit of genius and he's a
québécois artist and a carver sculptor
and I'd like to start by letting
Jonathan tell us who he is and and what
he does okay so yeah I'm an icon carver
which means that I am make I make
carvings for churches and for people of
traditional images so I get commissions
and I and I work within a traditional
language of Christian art meaning that
for about five years now full-time and
before that I actually lived in Africa
for seven years working with artisans
there trying to help them in their
business practices and their their
design skills so I have a very kind of
strange and varied background I studied
fine art at Concordia University here in
Montreal in the yeah in the late 90s oh
yeah so many full-time icon carvers do
you suppose there are in Canada in
Canada there they I'm the only one we're
about actually in the entire world where
we're very few I actually know most of
them um yeah yeah well it doesn't sound
like a very easy thing to monetize so
how didn't how in the world did you go
from being a an art student trained at
Concordia to being a carver of icons I
studied painting and drawing at
Concordia on the surface I was doing
really well I actually finished first in
my in my class but there was a malaise
the whole time I was working there
because I'm a Christian I grew up I grew
up a Christian and I was trying to
figure out how that would connect to my
art practice and so I was I was looking
trying to figure out symbolic languages
and in painting and trying to find ways
to talk about bigger bigger questions
metaphysical ideas in my paintings but I
didn't have the language so I was really
just groping around almost blind and
yeah and at the end of my time at
Concordia the professor who was
supervising me she she basically said on
the very last day she said what are you
doing here this is not this is not the
place for you after that I it kind of
left me dangling you know and and
questioning a lot of things so what sort
of education did you get at Concordia
all the fine arts programs now in I
think pretty much I was 100% of
based on contemporary art practices and
so very few universities very few
programs teach technical skills or teach
you you know how to draw in a classical
way so they actually not really teaching
anything it's hard to know exactly what
they're doing I guess it was ever since
the 1960s there has been this idea in in
the art world that technical skills and
ability just aren't that important and
that the important thing is to find your
I would say your political voice but
it's it's very strange to me that this
has occurred because it seems to me that
before your voice is anything but a an
off-color croak you have to become a
disciple of a discipline and an
apprenticeship and and learn the tools
and trades of your craft and learn how
to be an artist because there's a
technical end to that I mean this is
really almost an image of the world as
it stands now the the purpose or the the
stated purpose of of modern especially
postmodern art was to free the artist
right to break to break away all the the
things that were holding the artists
back in terms of rules and in terms of
of just the way things were presented
but what ended up happening is that
there were no more legit legit amaizing
objective or you know strong
legitimizing structures around the art
the only thing left was politics and
relationships and status basically so
hard you know wonders there's a big
literature on creativity and its strong
least which I know very well my lab
designed the creative achievement
questionnaire which is used it's been
used in hundreds of studies now to
assess lifetime creativity and so I've
spent a lot of time looking at the
measurement of creativity and also
trying to understand creativity and the
literature strongly suggest that when
you impose restrictions on people it
actually makes them more creative rather
than less because part of what
creativity is is the overcoming of
obstacles you know imagine someone who
writes poetry in the Haiku format well
it's it's very very restrictive and
obviously arbitrarily sold but the fact
of the restriction is partly what makes
the poetic form possible the same thing
is true if you think about playing a
game there's a there's far more things
that you can't do
when you play chess then there are
things that you can do but there's still
an infinite number of variations of
chess games so this idea that there's a
dichotomy between structure and rules
and creativity is is perniciously false
and contradicted by the evidence and
when you when you start to explore the
art world in the way it works is there's
an irony there that it purports to not
have boundaries on creativity and
structures on character but they're
actually extremely strict and they're
hidden there they're kind of this
pernicious thing underneath where we're
actually you you have to present things
in a very very precise way for it to be
able to to enter into the legitimizing
structure of the of the gallery it's
like the message that I was trying to
work on and the the structure of
contemporary art just didn't fit
together and so at some point I gave up
on art I had to work you know I had a
studio and I closed it down I just
destroyed all my paintings it was it was
actually a moment of kind of spiritual
crisis for me and it's in that in that
moment that I discovered many of
medieval art I discovered traditional
Christian art and when I discovered
traditional Christian art it was exactly
what you were saying before the forms of
Christian art were kind of developed as
a community would say as a Christian
community developed these forms that
were actually extremely powerful and and
created like a cosmic map basically and
so you could use you could use these
images as a type of algebra to create a
sacred sacred language and so
discovering that I just felt like yeah
it gave me so much possibility you know
you're going back like 800 years 900
years into the history even farther than
that back into the history of
traditional art so you say you
discovered Christian iconography and I
also know that you're you're you're an
Orthodox Christian which is a strange
thing for a Kaiba quoi so I don't know
you're a pretty rare bird so maybe you
could you could say a few words about
the discovery of the iconography how
that came about and also how it is that
you converted to Orthodox Christianity
well I mean those two things are very
you know intricately related I think
during during university just like
a lot of people I kind of got into an
intellectual and spiritual crisis I was
reading de la bugia and all the
postmodern theorists trying to wrap my
head around this like what does this
mean for me and what is it what is going
on and and it's in that kind of crazy
time that I started reading the Church
Fathers and and reading more traditional
reading more traditional authors people
who talk about traditions in different
different cultures and realizing that
this was really the solution for for me
at least it was the solution to kind of
get out it get out of the the chaos that
the modern world had kind of fallen into
and so it came with the art so looking
at the art and seeing the patterns
emerge and seeing that those patterns in
in the art were the same as you find in
Scripture and the same that you find in
liturgy and the same that you find in
the stories that are around us even
stories that aren't actually Christian
to see those patterns emerge is what
really caught my attention in and and so
I was looking at first I wasn't
necessarily going to be Orthodox I could
see the patterns coming through and I
was trying to you know trying to figure
out and I couldn't find them in my own
meter which is which I grew up
evangelical and so I I was looking for
it I couldn't find it I looked at
Catholicism but finally I felt that I've
been looking at orthodoxy I felt like
orthodoxy was the type of Christianity
that had preserved the most of that
ancient worldview and was still living
it today so it's a it's a living
tradition it you know when you say you
went back on 800 years in a way that's
true but it's not true in for the
Orthodox because they they continue to
perpetuate those those forums until
today I mean not that they didn't go
through rocky times obviously it's been
crazy for orthodoxy as well but for some
reason they've been able to constantly
revive their forums you know and today
it's a thriving a thriving part of
Christianity well you know did this this
idea of this of this return and and the
continual revivification of traditional
forms reminds me of two things it
reminds me of the old Egyptian stories
about Horace and Osiris and Horus is the
Egyptian god of
vision and attention so he's the
Egyptian I and and the Falken and after
Horus defeat Seth who's the sort of
Egyptian precursor to Satan and reclaims
his throne he goes down into the
underworld to rescue his father Osiris
who Seth had chopped up into pieces and
when he's down in the underworld he
gives Osiris one of his eyes which seth
has torn out he gives him one of his
eyes and then brings him back up to the
surface and they rule Egypt together and
and the union of Osiris and Horus was
like the Pharaohs soul so there's a this
ancient idea it's expressed in more
places than in Egyptian mythology that
it's the duty it's the sacred obligation
of someone who's awake to journey to the
underworld and revivify the corpse of
his father and that not unites the
individual with a living culture and
also makes the culture alive because of
course culture in some sense because
it's the product of of the dead is a
dead is a dead entity it has to be
continually revivified by the living and
then you see that echoed in more modern
form oddly enough in a Disney animated
movie in Pinocchio and Pinocchio is the
story of the struggle of a puppet a
marionette whose strings are being
pulled by forces that he does not
understand it's the story of his
struggle towards individuality and and
rebirth and a number of things happened
to pinocchio he has to learn not to lie
he has to learn not to be a neurotic
victim because that's actually one of
the temptations it's that it's it's his
agreement that he's a neurotic victim
that that places him on Pleasure Island
where he virtually where he's in danger
of becoming a jackass and a slave to
totalitarians
interestingly enough from after he
leaves Pleasure Island he goes to find
his father but he can't find him and a
note from the Holy Ghost essentially
tells him that his father is at the
bottom of the ocean in the belly of a
giant whale and the whale is also a
dragon and so then Pinocchio has to go
down to the bottom of the ocean in his
half jackass form and rescue his father
from the belly of the whale and he does
that by mastering fire and interestingly
enough
in the in the Pinocchio video he's
assimilated to the Christian symbol of
the fish in the belly of the in the
belly of the whale Geppetto couches a
bunch of fish he thinks to eat them and
then he couches Pinocchio and confuses
him with a fish doesn't realize that
having caught Pinocchio he's caught his
own salvation then they work together to
get out of the whale's belly but there's
this very old idea that especially in
chaotic times when everyone's turned
into a jackass and a tool of
totalitarians that the way forward is to
journey to the deepest possible recesses
of a reality and revivify the farther
something everyone needs to know and
there's something I mean we'll see as
our conversation continues you'll see
how how for me at least this goes is
that for me going back into the the
Christian tradition and and and
reconnecting with the Christian
tradition has actually opened my eyes
also to the world around me so those
patterns that I find in my own tradition
the patterns that are kind of feeding my
life once they're integrated now when
you look around you you see them they
appear everywhere right world is
actually made of those patterns and you
can recognize you can recognize those
patterns in contemporary you know
culture and and you watch a movie and
you can see that these these are the
same patterns but it's the best way it's
like the danger is to is to do it in an
innocent a simply in an intellectual way
I mean that's kind of our our danger so
connecting to a tradition you know
becoming orthodoxson and living it
through liturgy like liturgy when you go
to church and you participate in the
liturgy you're physically engaging in in
the sacred patterns and so it's it's a
way to make it almost a bodily
expression right oh it's interesting you
know the Christian emphasis on the
resurrection of the body which is of
course something that that modern people
have a very difficult time with I mean
people can perhaps swallow the notion
that the soul is immortal but the idea
of the resurrection of the body is
something that just seems beyond the
pale but there's there's a logic to that
insistence and the insistence is that
there's something sacred and necessary
about the body and that it can't be
forgotten
when discussing both spirituals say on
sacred matters so and it's definitely
the loss of the body that's part of what
what constitutes part of the the
rootless nihilism that characterizes the
moderate modern age and I learned that
partly by reading Carl Rogers because
one of the things that Rogers talked
about was the necessity Jung talked
about this a lot as well the necessity
of bringing the body into alignment with
with fir Rogers it was more with the
voice and he claimed for example that
you could feel with your body
essentially whether or not your words
were aligned properly with your being
and certainly I've certainly learned
that that's true and that you can learn
to determine when your voice is making
you stronger physically and when it's
making you weaker physically a very very
useful thing to to pay attention to one
of the iconic figures that you've carved
and that you're interested in is st.
George and I've been very interested in
the figure of st. George I think that
the the story that's encapsulated in st.
George is certainly one of the oldest
stories known to mankind it might be at
the core of the oldest story because
basically what it does is present human
being the individual in a in a in a
battle where the individual society and
the individual are being threatened by
the re-emergence or emergence of a
carnivorous reptilian carnivorous
predator and I think the roots of the
st. George story go all the way back to
the time when the distant ancestors of
human beings were living in trees and
beings and being preyed upon by
predatory snakes and that's about 60
million years ago back when there were
still dinosaurs by the way an
anthropologist named Lynn Isbell at the
at UCLA has done a series of studies
showing that the reason that human
beings have such amazing vision because
we can see better than any other animal
except for birds of prey is because our
vision evolved to help us detect
predatory snakes in particular as they
crept up on us through the underbrush
and
she established out by noting that there
was a powerful correlation between the
prevalence of predatory snake predation
in primate populations across the world
and the acuity of primate vision and
it's also the case that our vision
evolved just as the story in Genesis
suggests because of fruit because we see
colors because we can detect to detect
ripe fruit and so Genesis insists that
human beings got their vision because of
snakes and fruit and that seems exactly
right from an evolutionary perspective
but you can imagine the idea and st.
George there's a there's a dragon that
reemerge is from it's it's a lair
underground and it's a it's an eternal
dragon immortal dragon and it threatens
the community and Saint George goes out
to to fight the dragon in single combat
and as a consequence he he frees a
virgin from from the snakes grasp just
like Harry Potter does in the second
Harry Potter volume when he goes down
underneath Hogwarts to free Ginny who's
the virgin Virginia from the grips of
the basilisk and the Basques Liske is
the thing that turns you to stone with a
single glance and Harry Potter is
revivified by the way by the Phoenix's
tears and the Phoenix produces a rebirth
right because this the Phoenix is a
symbol of death and rebirth and so
there's the st. George story is is
embedded right in the depths of the
Harry Potter story but I think it's
predicated on the idea that human beings
men in particular forever have been
fighting off the predations of natural
and the social world and the the idea
that you free the virgin from the grasp
of the serpent is that women have
preferentially chosen to ally themselves
with and mate with men who are capable
of facing the reptilian predator and so
it's the basic evolutionary story of
mankind that human beings learn to fight
back against predators maybe to even
find them in their lair instead of
waiting for them to attack
and that women in their gratitude for
that in their gratitude for the
protection of infants like there's often
images of Mary raising Christ up out of
the way from a predatory reptile right
and that's in reference to the Genesis
comment that this that Mary will bruise
the head of the serpent with her heel
it's an extraordinarily extraordinarily
deep story it goes deeper than just the
idea of the serpent - because the
ultimate serpent in some sense isn't the
one that lives in the external world the
ultimate serpent might be the one that's
in the heart of your enemies or if you
make a metaphysical transformation in
your thinking even beyond that the
ultimate serpent isn't even the one that
lives in the heart of your enemies so
it's not the natural snake or the
crocodile or a predator like that it's
not the vicious barbarian that's come to
the gates of your castle - to steal your
belongings and make off with your women
it's the snake that lives in your heart
yeah and that's why Christianity except
it insists on the association between
the snake and the Garden of Eden and
Satan yeah the I mean I think that if
you if you if you think of the world in
terms of a macrocosm and microcosm the
idea that that certain structures repeat
themselves at different levels of
reality you know that's like music right
then you you you you can think of this
idea of a world as having in the middle
you know a tree or a cross or you know
something like an axis in the center and
as you move away from that access you
know from the axis which defines the
space basically like a flag or something
like a post as you move away from that
center you're moving further and further
from what it defines and you're
approaching a chaos basically right
you're approaching chaos which is within
the negative sense it's chaos right in
the positive sense it's also potential
it's the potential from which that world
will will grow so it on one side it
threatens the inside if you will and on
the other side it is the potential by
which that that thing will grow and so
that
again in the Virgin in in st. George's
story there there are actually several
versions of the of the dragon in some
virgins and the most known versions say
Saint George will kill the dragon but
there are lesser known versions of the
story where he actually tamed the dragon
and turns a dragon into his pet you know
and there's version where he tamed it
then kills it like there's different
versions of the of the story but it's to
show this idea of of as you move out
sometimes there's something on the edge
that that appears on the edge and you
can't define it it's this chaotic thing
it's the dragon in in traditional way of
representing it isn't just a reptile
it's actually a hybrid creature it it
usually has a mix of of lizard and it
has hairy feet and wings and and so it
is it's this yeah it's a monster it's
it's a it's a monster it's an
amalgamation of things to be frightened
by but also treasure because the dragon
doesn't only guard virgins it guards
treasure it's in the it's in contact
with what you fear and despise that the
treasure is to be found yeah they know
your your notion about the center point
say with the flag or the cross reminded
me reminded me of the way the children
react with their mother and their home
and so what a child will do when when he
or she is exploring the world is make
contact with the mother and that and
that's in the center of the household so
you could think about it as the mother
embedded in society the child will will
comfort himself with contact with the
mother and then go out into the world to
the point where his fear overcomes his
exploratory tendency and then on the on
that edge he'll play and further his
psychological development and his
mastery of the world and then when he
wears out and and maybe goes beyond his
limit he runs back to the center point
for comfort and then the next time he
goes out he can go out a little bit
farther yeah and so that that structure
basically that is basically the
structure of everything I mean you know
it's structure of a society it's a
structure of a family and like you said
it's also the structure of an individual
where on the on the edges of our person
we have these desires that exist on the
edge of our person and those desires are
very dangerous because they they can
lead us into a lot of a mess but they're
also uh but the the tool by which we
further ourselves like those that's very
similar against a Young's idea of the
incorporation of the shadow and also in
each his idea of beyond good and evil
I mean Nietzsche bat meant by that at
least in part beyond the conceptions of
good and evil that are basically thrown
up by nothing but cowardice right so you
try to make yourself into this little
restricted thing that's basically the
union persona and you define yourself as
good if you never go outside that little
box but to be truly good you have to go
way outside that box so if you think
take this as a as a worldview I mean
basically that that has become my own
worldview it helps you to identify
what's happening around you so on the on
the periphery of of the world there are
these marginal things that exist kind of
in the buffer between you know order and
and absolute chaos and those things they
they all you know they rear their heads
up and sometimes and so we have to have
a trend we transact with them in
different ways sometimes tame them
sometimes you have to you know you know
like a dragon you have to kill it
sometimes you have to just ignore it to
like great monsters just have to be left
alone basically like they're too big to
to deal with yet you just leave them
alone and to me this is really related
to what you're going through right now
it seems like this is where we are right
now in our society yeah our obsession
with liminal things right now in the
world seems to be a sign of something
you know the word monster actually comes
from the Latin word which means to show
right as a portent we in French we
actually still have the verb motivate
which means the show is it's promoting
demonstrating yes yeah there you go
demonstrate exactly so the word motto a
monster is is a portent of something it
is it's it's like a harbinger of of
change or harbinger that's something you
need to pay attention because something
is happening and so right now like so to
demonstrate to demonstrate is to D
maaan straight yes right it's - its to
take the monster apart and make it into
something that's you can deal with yes
that you can master yeah that's like
Marduk in the old Mesopotamian myth
because Marduk who is the Mesopotamian
hero God confronts timeout who's a
monster and cuts her into pieces and
makes the world and actually one of the
names of Marduk that the Mesopotamians
had was he who makes interesting and
useful things from the combat with time
out yeah yeah yeah I mean so so right
now we if you look around it if you
think of the social manifestation that
are going on like just take Tom B's for
example like that's the greatest example
because a zombie is an in-between figure
it's something that is neither dead nor
alive it's it stands in in-between two
categories and so this the in in the
case of the zombie the zombie because it
is in between the categories is act as a
parasite it starts to eat the interior
the brain actually exactly yes it's
looking for for for meaning and so it
wants to eat the thing that's that's
inside is trying to devour it right up
that's ohrp's of the culture like the
story of Oedipus and the Sphinx is is
the perfect kind of image of this so the
Sphinx appears as this undefined monster
right it's a mix of a woman and a lion
and a bird or whatever it's this thing
that appears and so and what it is it's
a question it's saying like what am i a
monster is a question or it's an enigma
the person coming for it is is faced
with this enigma and the danger so one
possibility is that you name the monster
and you're able to integrate it the
other possibility is that you're eaten
by the monster those two things are a
real reality right on the edge on the
edge of things so when you come to the
edge of something you know you have this
this this this image in traditional
stories of the bridge you come to the
end of something and there's a bridge
and on the bridge there's a there's a
monster and so you have to face this
monster because when you're on the
bridge you're in a dangerous place
you're in between you're not in between
categories right you're in no-man's land
you're in no-man's land
and so the monster comes and
wants to devour you so it can be either
this idea of the the monster asking
question asking an enigma for you to be
able to cross the bridge and so this is
what's happening right now right and so
there are some elements that come from
the margins of society which are saved
and the ones that I've been dealing with
or have been the people who don't fit
into the gender categories yes yes and
so that we're in a situation where we're
those that manifestation of of hybridity
right because because if you look at the
categories that are used they are they
are trying to be the category of
multiplicity itself yeah they're trying
to be the category for the mode that's
why the categories are multiplying
beyond name they started with just
non-binary and now it's up to 70 on
online yeah what it is it's a
decomposition like it's a decomposition
of a category you come to the end of
something and it starts to decompose I
know and your talk to talk about the raw
boroughs the servant eating its own tail
well this is my vision of it is that
when you first see that serpent youth it
actually looks like it's the tail that's
eating the head and then after a certain
transition then it becomes the head
eating the tail so imagine a fruit falls
on the ground the ground starts to eat
it it starts to decompose and once it's
fully decomposed then something happens
there's a flip and now the seed starts
to use the earth and eat the earth to
become a tree and so there's that moment
at the end of something where there's a
flip that happens like an inversion and
then an inversion of an inversion that
happens it's a very chaotic time and and
that's the moment where we we are in
right now and what you're going through
like the finger that you've you put your
finger on something very very critical
and that's why there's so much noise
about it is because you're you're
standing right in that spot and you're
pointing you're telling everybody pay
attention to this monster like it's
right there in front of us you know you
you talked before with me about two two
biblical stories that shed some light on
this and you were talking about Abraham
and the stranger and so maybe you could
walk through that because I thought that
was an extremely interesting analysis
okay so so I mean the way that in the
Bible and in most traditional societies
the way that you deal with the strange
okay the thing that comes from the
margins you know it's the stranger in in
a global way it's the strange thing the
way we deal with that is to hospitality
right the first way we deal with it
right the first way we deal with
something coming from the outside and
that doesn't fit into our world is
through hospitality so the hospitality
hospitality means that you receive this
thing as a as a stranger and there's
these implicit rules of how you interact
with them so that there isn't a mutual
destruction basically okay and so in the
Bible we see those a version of good
hospitality and bad hospitality play
themselves out so in the story of
Abraham Abraham receives three strangers
and he receives them into his tent and
he feeds them and he gives that you know
he receives them properly and the
strangers are also acting properly in
his tent you know they're eating his
food but they're being respectful of the
house they're not stealing things
they're not you know trying to seduce
his wife or doing the things that you're
not supposed to do implicitly when
you're in someone else's house and and
because of that the the three strangers
announced the Abraham that he's going to
have a child so Abraham is in his 90s
you know he never thought right they're
angels right they're secretly but
they're secretly angels that's what's
important is that in the strange the
strange because the strange is an
ambiguous a category it can contain both
extremes it can contain both the angel
and the devil right these three angels
come come to him and they announce that
he's going to have a child and so what
they do is that the strange now acts as
this potential that we talked about
right so it's a fructifying agent in
that batteries and so it's always the
case that like an orderly structure has
to allow an element of chaos on
an element of the strange into it in
order to become something new and even
to maintain its own survival because
things have to become something new as
they move forward through time right and
so in this in that case the stranger
becomes the the means by which Abraham's
marriage is is instructive so he grows
his family grows through this bright
interaction with the stranger okay right
so now these same three strangers then
they go to visit Abraham's brother lot
who's in Sodom and Gomorrah and then
although lot receives the strangers
appropriately the inhabitants of Sodom
and Gomorrah they want to rape these
these strangers at least they want to
sexually assault the strangers and rape
them and angels blind the people around
them and they're able to escape and
because of the the wrong interaction and
that the sexual the wrong sexual
interaction with the with the between
the stranger and the people of the city
it the city is destroyed by fire and
then it leads even further it leads to
lot having an incestuous relationship
with his daughters and so it's like the
whole world just kind of it collapses
because there isn't a proper approach to
hospitality and but it you know and in
that story you you see how it's active
so there's an intimation in there to is
that if the if the if the interaction
with the stranger is handled properly
then everything becomes more fruitful
and if the interaction with the stranger
upsets things say is basic as basic as
as sexual interactions between people
then the entire society can become
destroyed exactly and and in that Indian
and I'm using those two stories but but
those two those two stories repeat
themselves in all all this I mean
there's so many stories where you see
that often it's not just sex it's it's
often food there's sex and food those
are the two things that the two major
ways in which we integrate the world for
example like you the story of Hansel and
Gretel for example is a is a is a is a
perfect example of where the desire to
eat the people that to eat your or your
guests right right or for example their
mother
in the Hansel Gretel story because she's
too good to be true and then she's all
compassion the witch in the Hansel
Gretel story and you can tell that
because she has a ginger she has a
gingerbread house it's made of candy
yeah and like a house made of candy is
too good to be true that's the social
justice warrior over emphasis on
compassion and inside she's just
fattening the kids up constantly taking
care of them but her fundamental wish is
to devour them yeah so like an example
and they sort of one more thing they've
been abandoned those kids have been
abandoned the predations of the evil
mother because the family broke down
like they're it's it's the stepmother
who tells the father if I remember
correctly to abandon the children in the
forest yeah yeah so it's the breakdown
of the family that leads to the children
being threatened by the oedipal mother
who's too good to be true she's
compassion that's gone completely beyond
it's it's it's it's tolerable limit yeah
yeah so so shanira tale that's for sure
you see that you see that I think
there's this sorry there's so many
stories of how the the relationship
between a host and a stranger goes goes
wrong like there's an in the push comes
from the host and sometimes the push can
come from the guests like there's a
there's an Ethiopian tradition where
it's almost an inversion of Abraham's
story where a burglar man receives three
guests into his home and the three
guests serve Him food which which ends
up being a human being the net heat so
he they kind of trick the the host into
becoming a cannibal and then the host
becomes like an out-of-control cannibal
and you know he's eating people all over
the place so you can see how the story
can go both ways like the the the
relationship with the strange there can
be a push from the inside from the the
right hand let's say the order hand
there can be a push towards up that
causes the chaos but it can also come
from the the guest can also come from
the stranger which can push from his
side or you know from their side and
then create the chaos
you